Guide to the Mirra Ginsburg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Subseries II.2: Organizations
    - Penguin Books; Viking Penguin Inc. The Ultimate Threshold, New York, NY, Jan. 1978 - Mar. 1982 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Gouch, Patricia Lee; Wiseman, Paula Philomel Books; The Putnam Publishing Group Clay Boy. Book Report: Dubov, N, The Runaway., New York, NY, Nov. 1989 - Nov. 1992 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      [See also Authors Guild]
    - Culler, Shirley; Hoffman, Berenice; Random House Zamiatin, Evgenii, New York, NY, Aug. 1961 - Apr. 1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      [Random House correspondence with Toni Morrison is filed under Cataloged Correspondence - Morrison, Toni;]
    - Phillips, Sydney S. G. Phillips Inc. Last Door to Aiya, New York, NY, Sep. 1967 - Apr. 1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Anderson, Elliot; Newman, Charles Tri-Quarterly - Northwestern University Remizov, Evanston, IL, Mar. 1972 - Nov. 1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Fitchen, Allen N.; Philipson, Morris; Young, Bruce University of Chicago Press A Soviet Heretic: Essays by Yevgeniy Zamyatin; Zamiatin, Evgenii - Plays (rejected), The Dragon, Chicago, IL, Jan. 1967 - May. 1991 (Box 9, Folder 11 - 12)
    - University of Chicago Press Reviews and Ads for The Soviet Heretic, Chicago, IL, 1970 - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Shale, Alida; Sifton, Elizabeth The Viking Press Zamiatin, We; New York, NY, Oct. 1971 - Jun. 1983 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Guarnascelli, Maria; Laychak, Mary; Queen, Lisa William Morrow & Co. New York, NY, Mar. 1975 - Jan. 1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      [See alse Greenwillow Books]
    - Kraus, Robert Windmill Books, New York, NY, Nov. 1974 - Jun. 1976 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Brent, Jonathan Yale University Press re: translation of Diary of Kornei Chukovskii. Includes samples of original Russian text and various translations, New Haven, CT, May 1993 - Aug. 1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.3: Subject Files
    Arranged Chronologically
    - Aisenschtadt, Liuba; Vikhman, Galia; [...], Ava; [...], Berta; [...], Niusha, [...]; Liza; [...], Rafail; School Friends from Libava, Libava, Latvia, 1925 - 1927 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - [...], Sarah; [...], Esther; [...], Mildred; [...], Rivka; [...], Bella. School Friends from Montreal, Montreal, Canada, 1927 - 1930 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Letters to family from Mirra and Lily Ginsburg, Gloversville, NY, Jun. - Aug. 1942 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Beddoe, Josephine; Commire, Anne; Kay, Ernest Gale Research Company, International Biographical Centre, Biography International Biographical Enries on Ginsburg. Publications: Directory of British and American Writers, Dictionary of International Biography, Contemporary Authors, Who's Who of American Women; The World Who's Who of Women, The International Authors and Writers Who's Who; The World Who's Who of Authors, 1969 - 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Correspondence, 1931 - 1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Subseries II.4: Other
    Arranged alphabetically by author (personal or corporate)
    - Aguirre, Gary J.; Aleksander, Irina; Anderson, David; Anderson, Paul B. - see YMCA;[Argus], M. K.; Arno, Enrico; Aronian, Sona; Avnet, Rosalind; Babyonyshev, Sarra; Bakst, Elana Sarah; Barton, Byron (outgoing); Beil, Frederick C.; Bell, Pearl K.; Benedikt, Michael; Benn, Anna; [Berkowitz], Mitchell; Bespalova, [Larisa]; Bird, Thomas E.; Borishansky, Elliot; Braginsky, Tania and Aleksandr; [Brittain], Vera; Brudne, Eva; Buehl, Ron - see Dell Publishing Co. American Folklore Society; American Translators Association; Asia Society; The Babbling Bookworm; Beauty and the Beast Storytellers; Correspondence: A - B (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Cannon, Kristin; Casanova, Mercedes; Chalidze, Vera; Chute, Joy; Codray Natalie; Corzin, Steven - See Columbia University Libraries; Costlow, Jane; Cote, Maureen; Crafton, John - see Dover Publications; Graig, Jean; Curley, Laurie; Curtis, Frank; Cushman-Miller, Kathleen - see D.C. Heath & Co.; Cuyler, Margery; De Donato, Diego; Delap, Richard; Deshell, Maier - see Jewish Publication Society; Donovan, John - see Children Book Council; Dorfman, Jeannette; Caedmon Records; Candlewick Press; Chelsea Theater Center of Brooklyn; Children Book Council; Columbia University Libraries - Bakhmeteff Archive; Curtis Brown, Ltd.; D.C. Heath & Co.; Dell Publishing Co.; Dover Publications; Dramatists Guild; Dramatists Guild Quarterly Correspondence: C - D (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Ebon, Martin - see Playboy Press; Eilan, Arieh; Elinson, Genry; Epstein, Natalie & Joseph; Erlich, S.; Etkind, [E.]; Fabricant, Mona; Farrell, MacLennan; Filipoff, Boris; Fischer, George; Fletcher, Edward A.; Flower, Mary; Frankel, Richard - see Chelsea Theater Center of Brooklyn; Francis, Barbara - see Prentice Hall; Frenaye, Frances; Freedgood, Anne; Friedman, Ernestine L.; Geier, Fred and Nora; Geier, Frederic M. and Susan; Geier, Len and Gloria; Gershkovich, Alexander; Gir[lant], Lynn; Girshin, Mark; Gollancz, Livia; Gotlieb family; Graham, Patricia Albjerg - see Radcliffe Institute; Greenfeld, Howard; Grinberg, Victor; Grodman, Bea and Manny; Grodman, Lawrence K.; Guarnaschelli, Maria - see William Morrow & Co. Easton Press; Envision Entertainment; Esquire Magazine; Ginn & Co; Grany; Guggenheim Foundation - See John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation Correspondence: E - G (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Haugh, Richard; Halbert, Nancy L.; Halpert, Carol - see Caedmon Records; Heacock, Paul - see Perigee Books; Hills, Rust - see Esquire Magazine; Howe, Irving; Huff, Barbara - see Junior Literary Guild; Jacobson, Ruth; Jones, Phillip; Jurasas, Jonas; H. W. Wilson Company; Hamish Hamilton Ltd.; Highlights For Children; Indiana University Library; Inter-Language Literary Associates; Internal Revenue Service; International Rescue Committee; Iskander Ltd.; Jewish Publication Society; John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation; Junior Literary Guild. Correspondence: H - J (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Kadin, Daniel Scot; Kalfin, Robert - see Chelsea Theater Center of Brooklyn; Kan, [Maria] (Musia); Katz, Shlomo; Kellman, Lillian; Khomiakov, Gennadii; Kiselev, Alexey A.; Klein, Judith - see Highlights For Children; Klose, Eliza; Kosterin family; Kovarsky, Vera; Kramer, Hilton; Kresh, Paul; Krotkov, IUrii [Karlin, George]; Ktorova, Alla (Sander, Victoria); Kuz'min, Nikolai Kerlan Collection (University of Minnesota) - see Nelson, Karen Correspondence: K (Box 12, Folder 1)
      [Kiselev - enclosed arctile on Platonov's Kotlovan (The Foundation Pit); ]
    - Labedz, Chester S., Jr; Lane, Helen; Lang, Olga; Lanning, George; Lanskoy, Yevgeny (Evgenii); Lawrence, Starling - see W. W. Norton & Co.; Lebedev, Fedor; Levin, Elena; Levin, Vadim; Levine, Berta; Levitas, Mitchel; Lipson, Rita; Lokshina, Valeria; Lubensky, Sophia; Luplow, Carol; Lurie, Lisa; Mackler, Mary; Magidoff, Robert; Marlow, Marilyn -see Curtis Brown, Ltd.; Martins, Peter; Matlaw, Mrs. Myron; Menendez, Aurora; Miller, Tina - See Ginn & Co.; Mills, Robert P.; Mora, Barbara; Muchnic, Helen Ladies Home Journal; Leifer & Youdelman; Library of Congress - Slavic and Central European Division; McDougal, Littell & Co.; McGraw-Hill Companies; Correspondence: L - M (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Nedela, George; Nelson, Karen; Nickson, Richard; Obolensky, Ludmila; Ohly, Nick and Sara; Olsoufieva, Maria; Oppenheim, Joanne - see Oppenheim Toy Portfolio National Public Radio; National Register of Prominent Americans; National Writers Union; New York Public Library; New Yorker Magazine; Noonday Press; North Point Press; Novoye Russkoye Slovo; Novyi Mir; NYNEX; Oppenheim Toy Portfolio Correspondence: N - O (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Payne, Robert; Pennant, Edmund; Pia, Pamela - see Easton Press; Pirog, Gerald; Pollett, Elizabeth; Pope, Martin; Prashker, Betty; Ptacek, Gloria; Rechtin, Rita; Reed, Phyllis A.; Reginald, Robert; Reiner, Paula; Rifkin Sterling, Nancy; Robinson, John; Roman, Amy; Rosenstein, Sylvia J.; Rosenthal, Charlotte Perigee Books/Putnam Publishing Group; Playboy Press; Popular Library/Fawcett Books; Prentice Hall; Princeton University Library; Publishers Weekly; Radcliffe Institute; Correspondence: P - R (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Sadomskaya, Natalia; Sahdev, Deshdeep; Sample, Norman; Scheffler, Leonore; Schroeter, Leonard; Schmookler, Yulia; Schneider, Alan; Seidelman, [Berta]; Seldes, Timothy; Sergeev, A. (Kapralov, Anatolii); Shub, Elizabeth (Libby); [Silnicky], Larisa; Sinany, Helene; Sinclair, Kim - see H. W. Wilson Company; Skir, Leo; Smith, Edith A.; Smith, Roger - see Publishers Weekly; Sokol, Elena; Sol'skii, V.; Somlyo, Roy A.; Sperry, Ralph; Stacy, R. H.; Steefel, Jeffrey; Stephenson, Jane; Sutherland, Zena Societe de Gens de Lettres; Story Magazine; Correspondence: S (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Tafuri, Nancy; Thompson, Ralph; Tinsley, Royal L.; Tuttle, Cheryl; Villicana, E. C.; Vinkovetskii, Yakov & Diana; Voronina, Lidiia; Vovsi-Mikhoels, Natalia; Wallis, Nigel; Weiant, Edmund T.; Wilkinson, Natasha; Wilson, Tyrell; [Wisotsky], Sam; Wittlin, Joseph; Wohl, John; Woland, James; Wolberg family; Wolfson, Barbara; [Yakushev], Evgeniia; IUrieva, Zoia (Yurieff, Zoya I.); Zaslow, Shana University of California Press; Victor Kamkin, Inc.; W. W. Norton & Co.; William Morrow & Co; Woman's Home Companion; Yale University Library; YMCA; Correspondence: T - Z (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series III: Writings
  - Subseries III.1: Translations of Russian Authors
    Edited and final typescipts, notes, ms. drafts, page proofs, galleys. Includes essays by Ginsburg relating to the authors.
    - Aitmatov, Chingiz The White Ship (Belyi parokhod) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Alekseev, [...] Why did we come here..., New York, Nov. 18, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      [Soviet Diplomat, who escaped to USA from Soviet Legation in Mexico (1946?)]
    - Alekseeva. Nina Student Years [Memoirs], [May 1949] (Box 13, Folder 3)
      [Wife of Soviet Diplomat, who escaped to USA from Soviet Legation in Mexico (1946?)]
    - Babel, Isaac The End of The Poorhouse (Konets bogadel'ni), Apr. 1948 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Babel, Isaac Ilya Isaakovich and Margarita Prokofievna (Il'ia Isaakovich I Margarita Prokof'evna). Includes galleys for Midstream under the title "Regards to Odessa", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Babel, Isaac The Journey (Doroga), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Babel, Isaac Sunset (Zakat), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Babel, Isaac Sunset (Zakat) galleys for Noonday Press, [1960] (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Babel, Isaac Sunset (Zakat) - early versions, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Babel, Isaac Sunset (Zakat) - inserts, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Babel, Isaac (about); Nikolaevskii, B. The Fate of I. S. Babel., n.d.[1940s] (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Babel, Isaac (about) Translator's Notes (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Bakhnov, Vladlen Twelve Holidays (Box 13, Folder 13)
      [From The Air of Mars and Other Stories of Space and Time]
    - Beliaev, A. "In the Crooked Mirror of Sovietology"("V Krivom Zerkale Sovetologii"), [1972] (Box 13, Folder 14)
      [Article published in Pravda, Mar. 14, 1972]
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Bliss (Blazhenstvo) - photocopy of edited typescript. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Bliss (Blazhenstvo) - versions and drafts (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Bliss (Blazhenstvo) - ms. notes and background (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Flight (Beg) - edited typescript, [1969] (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Flight (Beg) - summary typescript (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Flight (Beg) - Introduction (edited typescript) (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Flight (Beg) - ms notes and background (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich The Life of Monsieur De Moliere (Zhizn' Gospodina de Mol'era)- edited typescript (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich The Life of Monsieur De Moliere (Zhizn' Gospodina de Mol'era) - translator preface (including notes, drafts and galleys) (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich The Life of Monsieur De Moliere (Zhizn' Gospodina de Mol'era) - ms notes and background (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Master and Margarita (Master I Margarita) - Introduction drafts (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Master and Margarita (Master I Margarita) - ms notes and background (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Master and Margarita (Master I Margarita) - notes and letter drafts re:comparison of Ginsburg and Glenny translations, [1967] (Box 14, Folder 13)
      [See also correspondence with Blake Hill, Patricia, New York Times Book Review, and Publishers Weekly]
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich (about) Biographical Notes on Bulgakov by MG - edited typescripts (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich (about) Mikhail Bulgakov:The Fate of a Soviet Writer (essay) - edited typescripts (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Ookie-Spooky (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Besy - sample translation by MG of first few pages (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Notes From Underground (Zapiski Iz Podpol'ia) - Edited Typescripts (Box 15, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Notes From Underground (Zapiski Iz Podpol'ia) - retyped pages (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Notes From Underground (Zapiski Iz Podpol'ia)- translator's note (edited typescripts) (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Notes From Underground (Zapiski Iz Podpol'ia)- notes and drafts (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Gogol', Nikolai Vasil'evich The May Night (Maiskaia Noch') - fragment, [1930s] (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Granin, Daniil "And Yet...", [1967] (Box 15, Folder 8)
      [Translation of article, written for the No. 1, 1967 Issue of Inostrannaia Literatura.]
    - Iordanashvili, E. Objective Meoylla (Box 15, Folder 9)
      [Translation published in Ultimate Threshold anthology]
    - Ivanov, Vsevolod The Encounter, [1930s] (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Kataev, Valentin Bearded Infant (Borodatyi Maliutka); Turmoil, [1930s] (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Kosterina, Nina Diary of Nina Kosterina, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      [Includes Russian text with notes by MG]
    - Kuprin, A. I. (Aleksandr Ivanovich) Hero, Leander, and the Shepherd, [1930s] (Box 15, Folder 13)
      [Published in Story magazine, Sep. 1934 - first publication of MG]
    - Nabokov, Vladimir The Calamity; The Port, [1930s] (Box 15, Folder 14)
      [From Vozvarshchenie Chorba, Berlin: Slovo, 1930]
    - Obukhova, Lidiia Lilith (Lilit) - Edited typescripts (Box 15, Folder 15 - 16)
      [Published in English as Daughter of the Night]
    - Obukhova, Lidiia Lilith (Lilit) - retyped pages and notes (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Obukhova, Lidiia Lilith (Lilit) - Edited photocopy of typescript (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Parnov, Eremei. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      [See Yemtsev, M; Parnov, Eremei.]
    - Pasternak, Boris (about) Boris Pasternak and the Union of Soviet Writers: stenographic record of the Moscow writers meeting, Oct. 31, 1958, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Pil'niak, Boris Wormwood (fragments), Mar. 1932 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Platonov, Andrei Foundation Pit (Kotlovan) - edited typescript & additional pages. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Platonov, Andrei Foundation Pit (Kotlovan) - edited typescript (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Platonov, Andrei Foundation Pit (Kotlovan) - uncorrected page proofs (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Platonov, Andrei Foundation Pit (Kotlovan) - introduction (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Platonov, Andrei Foundation Pit (Kotlovan) - notes (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Prishvin, Mikhail The Dappled Horse, [1930s] (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Razgovorov, Nikita Four Fours (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Remizov, Aleksei Edited typescripts and drafts (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Remizov, Aleksei (about) "Translating Remizov" - talk at a conference on A. Remizov, Amherst College, Amherst, MA, May 1985 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Remizov, Aleksei (about) Translating Remizov - notes (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Romanov, Panteleimon The Bad Number; The Kulaks (Kulaki), [1930s] (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Sapgir, Genrikh The Ogre and the Princess (Printsessa i Liudoed), notes (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Shvarts, Evgenii, Summary of four plays (Golyi Korol'; Ten'; Drakon, Obyknovennoe Chudo) (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Suteev, Victor What Kind of Bird Is That (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Teffi, N. A. The Unalive Beast, [1940s] (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Lieteunant Kije (Podporuchik Kizhe) - edited typescripts (Box 17, Folder 9 -10)
      [Alternative title by MG - Lietenant Nants]
    - Tynianov, IUrii Lieteunant Kije (Podporuchik Kizhe) - ms draft (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Young Vitushishnikov (Maloletnii Vitushishnikov) - edited typescripts (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Young Vitushishnikov (Maloletnii Vitushishnikov) - ms drafts and rewritten pages (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Introduction for Eridanos Press edition - edited typescripts (Box 18, Folder 2)
      [Edition included Lieteunant Kije and Young Vitushishnikov]
    - Tynianov, IUrii Introduction for Eridanos Press edition - notes (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Eridanos Press edited page proofs (Box 18, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Tynianov, IUrii Three Tsars proposal (proposal for collection of three novellas: Lieteunant Kije, Young Vitushishnikov, The Wax Figure ) (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Tynianov, IUrii (about) Notes for Tynianov translation (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Yemtsev, M; Parnov, Eremei. The Fall of the Supernova (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich The Flea (Blokha) - [final] typesctipt (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich The Flea (Blokha) - edited typesctipt (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Soviet Heretic (essays) - Edited Typescripts (Box 19, Folder 6 - 8)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Soviet Heretic (essays) - Notes (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich We (My) - edited typescript (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich We (My) - introduction (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich We (My) - notes and revisions (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Introduction to The Dragon (draft) (Box 20, Folder 5)
      [The Dragon - a collection of 15 short stories, translated by MG, published 1967]
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Notes on Zamiatin (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Reprints of essays: Backstage, H. G. Wells, 1969 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III.2: Folk and fairy tales
    - Folk Tale Anthologies
      Anthology files include proposals, sample translations, page proofs, illustrations and notes.
      - Russian Fable, Folk and Fairy Tales anthology - proposal and sample translations, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - How It Came to Be - Rissian Folk Tales (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Regional Folk Tales anthology proposal, translations: Genta (Udege); Kheverik (The Lazies) - (Tuvan); The Mare's Head (Russian); Birch Sap; The Fox and the Magpies; How the Fox Became Red; The Pretty Chipmonk (Altai), [1970s] (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - The Master of the Winds - Tales from Siberia, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - The Kaha Bird - Tales from the Steppes of Central Asia, [1971 - 1973] (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - How Wilka Went to Sea - Tales from West of Urals, [1970s] (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - 12 Clever Brothers and Other Fools anthology - edited typescripts, [1982] (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Adaptations of Single tales
      - The Apple Seed (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Clay Boy and The Little White Goat With The Golden Horns (Russian) (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - The Horse and the Ox (Latvian) (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Kitten From 1 To 10 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Little Rystu (Altai tale) (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Living Water (Tofalar) (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - The Magic Stove (Russian) (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - The Night It Rained Pancakes (Rissian) (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Striding Slippers (Udmurt) (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Subseries III.3: Singer
    - Translations
      Translations (all but one from Yiddish to English) made 1959 - 1966. Edited typescripts (often multiple versions), notes, sometimes other related material.
      - Altele (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Big and Little (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Gimpel-Durak (Gimpel the Fool) and an introductory article (Box 21, Folder 16)
        [Translation from Yiddish to Russian]
      - A Jewish Writer and the Yiddish Writer (Box 21, Folder 17)
      - The Lecture (Box 21, Folder 18)
      - The One Who Was Called Back (Box 21, Folder 19)
      - The Slaughterer (Box 21, Folder 20)
      - Taibele and Hurmizah (Box 21, Folder 21)
      - The Wager (Box 21, Folder 22)
      - Yash, the Chimney Sweep (Box 21, Folder 23)
      - Zeitl and Rickel (Box 21, Folder 24)
      - Yiddish originals (Forward newspaper clippings), 1959 - 1966 (Box 21, Folder 25)
      - Translator's Notes, [1960s] (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - Subseries III.4: Singer Book project
    - Interviews - Edited Typescripts, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Interviews - first version, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Notes and background Material (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Subseries III.5: Singer Book projectAnthologies
    Translations, proposals and notes for anthologies (for anthologies of folk tales see Tales subseries). Alphabetical by title
    - Dead Fiddler - texts and notes, [1959] (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - The Fatal Eggs - corrected page proofs, cover, notes. (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Ultimate Threshold - Preface, notes and drafts (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III.6: Singer Book projectEssays and notes
    Essays and miscellaneous notes
    - Young Voices in Soviet Literature (research paper published by the Independent Service for Information on the Vienna Youth Festival) (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Russian Revolutionary Movements - essay, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Children's Authors - essay, Feb. 1992 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Talks on Translation (various conferences), 1973 - [1990s] (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Early notes and drafts, [1929 - 1930s] (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Notes on Tales and Poems for Children, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Notes and drafts on K. I. Chukovskii, [1965 - 1969] (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Kaverin, Veniamin Notes on books by Kaverin (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Notes on Bible in Eastern and Western Cultures, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - [Notes in Yiddish], n.d. (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Notes on depression and dreams, 1972 - 1993 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous notes, [1973 - 1993] (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Background materials
  Research material used by MG in her works, such as original texts of translated authors, and writings about these authors. Series also include adaptations and reviews of translations by MG (additional reviews, sent by publishers, can be found in Arranged Correspondence series).
  - Subseries IV.1: Singer Book projectBulgakov
    Includes all materials relating to Bulgakov, exept translations and essays by MG (see Writings)
    - Original texts
      - Blazhenstvo (Bliss) - Russian text (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Ranniaia meizdannaia proza - Russian text (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Chudakova, M. Neokonchennoe sochinenie Mikhaila Bulgakova, includes previously unpublished works and letters by Bulgakov (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - About Bulgakov
      - Chudakova, M. "Zhizneopisanie Mikhaila Bulgakova", Moskva magazine, 1987 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Shwarts, Anatolii Zhizn' i smert' Mikhaila Bulgakova, with notes by MG (Box 24, Folder 5)